Inventory of the National Council for Prevention of War. Western Office (San Francisco) records
Hoover Institution Archives
National Council for Prevention of War. Western Office (San Francisco) records
1921-1943
43005
National Council for Prevention of War. Western Office (San Francisco).
4 manuscript boxes (1.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives. Stanford, California 94305-6010
Leaflets, pamphlets, press releases, and serial issues, relating to movements for peace, disarmament, preservation of American neutrality during World War II, and opposition to conscription and military training in educational institutions.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1943.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
The National Council for Prevention of War (NCPW) was founded by Frederick J. Libby on October 21, 1921, as the National Council for Limitation of Armaments. Later evolving into the National Council for Prevention of War, the American pacifist organization had a mission to prevent a trans-Pacific war through progressive world organization, the reduction of armaments by international agreement, and global education for peace.
The NCPW cooperated with other like-minded organizations, fighting policies that would increase armaments, and circulating educational resources such as pamphlets, fliers, and newsletters. The original office was in Washington D.C., and the San Francisco office was the first branch site opening in 1924.
Scope and Content of Collection
Collection contains leaflets, pamphlets, press releases, serial issues, plays, and program agendas issued by the National Council for Prevention of War (NCPW) with the objective to mobilize U.S. citizens and prevent the trans-Pacific war of 1941.
The materials are educational in nature; the leaflets, pamphlets, and correspondence attempt to inform the average citizen on the relevant politics of war. The NPCW encouraged political participation and active community involvement.
A significant portion of the materials are anti-war songs, plays, and pageants revealing the public nature of this organization. NCPW educational literature also targeted children and young adults in an effort to create a generation of internationally-minded citizens. The NPCW was primarily concerned with trans-Pacific issues, but also had a small focus on issues in Mexico.
The personal binder is a scrapbook of NCPW literature. There are bulletins about international education, letters encouraging political mobilization, and religious anti-war materials. There are maps outlining Congressional districts and lists of members of the House Representatives.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Disarmament.; Military education--United States.; Draft--United States.; Pacifism.; Peace.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; United States--Neutrality.
Collection Contents
- Information on National Council for Prevention of War (NCPW), 1935-1939 (File 1: 1)
- NCPW Correspondence, 1935-1939 (File 1: 2)
- Peace Propaganda: Bulletins, Newsletters, and other materials, 1926-1943 (File 1: 3)
- Bulletins, 1916-1934 (File 1: 4)
- Youth Based Peace Movements and Peace Education, 1924-1932 (File 1: 5)
- Economic Cost of War, 1930-1938. (File 1: 6)
  Includes cartoon poster on the cost of war
- Women against War, 1928-1939 (File 1: 7)
- Revision of Covenant of League of Nations, 1936 (File 1: 8)
- US-Mexico Literature, 1927 (File 1: 9)
- Anti-war Educational Resources for American Children, 1934-1936 (File 2: 1)
- Memorial Day service programs and literature, 1927-1929 (File 2: 2)
- Christmas-themed anti-war propaganda: songs, plays, and other materials, 1929-1940 (File 2: 3-4)
- Anti-war plays, songs, and programs, 1921-1935 (File 2: 5)
- Anti-war plays and programs, 1925-1929. (File 2: 6)
  Includes posters of the Kellogg Peace Pact
- Anti-war plays and programs, 1928-1936 (File 2: 7-9)
- Anti-war poems, plays, and programs, 1928 (File 3: 1)
- Speculations on future warfare, 1921-1929 (File 3: 2)
- Labor anti-war documents, 1922-1927 (File 3: 3)
- Labor anti-war Documents, 1912-1939 (File 3: 4)
- NCPW relevant Congressional records and statements, 1927-1939 (File 3: 5)
- Anti-compulsory military training literature, 1925-1930 (File 3: 6)
- Religious anti-war literature, 1924-1939. (File 3: 7)
- Keep America Out of War Congress, 1938-1939 (File 3: 8)
- NCPW informational literature, 1927-1939 (File 3: 9-10, File 4: 1)
- Scrapbook with NCPW articles and literature, 1929-1935 (File 4: 2-3)
- NCPW pamphlets, circa 1935 (File 4: 4)